<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A Full and true relation of the great and wonderful revolution that hapned lately in the kingdom of Siam in the East-Indies giving a particular account of the seizing and death of the late king, and of the setting up of a new one : as also of the putting to death of the king's only daughter, his adopted son never before published in any language, and now translated into English.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 56 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 17 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A40595</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12251576</idno>
  <idno type="VID">57118</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240946160</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing F2324</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R7232</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">12251576</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A40595)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 57118)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 144:6)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A Full and true relation of the great and wonderful revolution that hapned lately in the kingdom of Siam in the East-Indies giving a particular account of the seizing and death of the late king, and of the setting up of a new one : as also of the putting to death of the king's only daughter, his adopted son never before published in any language, and now translated into English.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], viii, 22 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Randal Taylor ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1690.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Harvard University Libraries.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="geographic_name">Thailand --  History --  To 1782.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08 </date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-02 </date>
            <label>Alexis (Ali) Jakobson </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-02 </date>
            <label>Alexis (Ali) Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:57118:1"/>
            <p>A FULL and TRUE RELATION OF THE <hi>Great and Wonderful REVOLƲTION</hi> That hapned lately in the KINGDOM of SIAM <hi>In the East-Indies.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Giving a particular Account of the Seizing and Death of the Late King, and of the Setting up of a New One.</p>
            <p>AS ALSO Of the putting to Death of the King's only Daughter, His Adopted Son who was a Christian, his two Brothers; And of Monsieur <hi>Constance,</hi> his great Minister of State, and Favourer of the <hi>FRENCH.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>AND Of the Expulsion of all the Jesuits, Missionary Priests, Officers and Soldiers of the <hi>FRENCH</hi> Nation out of that Kingdom, that endeavoured to bring it under the <hi>FRENCH</hi> Domination.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Being the Substance of several Letters writ in</hi> Octob. 1688. <hi>and</hi> Febr. 1689. <hi>From</hi> SIAM, <hi>and the Coast of</hi> Cormandel. <hi>Never before publisht in any Language, and now Translated into</hi> English.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Randal Taylor</hi> near <hi>Stationers-Hall.</hi> 16<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:57118:2"/>
            <pb n="i" facs="tcp:57118:2"/>
            <head>The Preface to the Reader.</head>
            <p>FOR the better understanding of the following Relation, I Think it not amiss to acquaint the Reader, That the first Solemn Embassy that the <hi>French</hi> King sent to the late King of <hi>SIAM,</hi> was in the Year 1685, by Monsieur <hi>de Chaumont,</hi> who went in Quality of Ambassador Extraordinary, whereof there are two Relations publisht; One, of the Embassy done by the Ambassador himself; The other, of the Voyage done by Father <hi>Tachard,</hi> one of the six Jesuits that accompany'd Monsieur <hi>de Chaumont</hi> in that Voyage, by the <hi>French</hi> King's particular Command. Both are Translated into <hi>English,</hi> Illustrated with Sculptures, and Printed about two Years ago.</p>
            <p>The second Embassy was performed in the Year 1687, when the <hi>SIAM</hi> Ambassadors that came into <hi>France</hi> the Year be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore with Monsieur <hi>de Chaumont,</hi> return'd back again into <hi>SIAM,</hi> by Messieurs <hi>de la Louberc</hi> and <hi>Ceberet,</hi> who carry'd over with them twelve <hi>French</hi> Jesuits, all Mathematicians, to teach the Christian Religion, and the Mathematical Sciences in the two Royal Cities of <hi>SIAM</hi> and <hi>LOUVO,</hi> and a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>siderable Body of Officers and Soldiers that the <hi>French</hi> King sent to the King of <hi>SIAM.</hi> The Relation of this second Voy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age is publisht only in <hi>French</hi> about six Months ago, by the same Father <hi>Tachard,</hi> who went back into <hi>SIAM</hi> with the <hi>SIAM</hi> Ambassadors, and return'd from Thence into <hi>France</hi> with the Character of the King of <hi>SIAM</hi>'s Envoy Extraordinary to the <hi>French</hi> King, and to the Pope. He arrived at <hi>Paris</hi> in <hi>No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vember, 1688.</hi> and had an Audience of the <hi>French</hi> King: And in <hi>January, 1689.</hi> he came to <hi>Rome,</hi> and had his Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience
<pb n="ii" facs="tcp:57118:3"/> of the Pope. In <hi>March</hi> following he was to have Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barqued the third time for <hi>SIAM;</hi> but what is become of him since, is not yet known.</p>
            <p>In all these three Relations there is mention made of a young Princess, Daughter to the late King of <hi>SIAM,</hi> that was then alive, whereof there is no Notice taken in the following Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of the late Revolution; but in other Letters that are come into <hi>France</hi> from other hands, we find a no less Tragical Account of her Death, than that of her Ʋnkles, and adopted Brother, the manner whereof they say was this: <hi>Opra Pitra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chard</hi> having dispatched the King's two Brothers, and adopted Son, who were the only Princes that stood in his way to the Crown, caused the young Princess, the King's only Daughter, to be taken and thrust into a large velvet Sack, and her Brains to be knockt out with great Bars of the sweet and so much esteem'd Wood in all the <hi>Indies</hi> call'd <hi>Aquila</hi> and <hi>Calamboar;</hi> and then thrown into the River, it being accounted a prophane thing, and a violation of the Sacred Respect due to a Princess of the Royal Blood of <hi>SIAM,</hi> to be put to Death in the usual manner that others are; and therefore they did it with great Deference and distinguishing Ceremonies becoming her Quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, not suffering her Royal Person to be polluted with the touch of any vulgar Hand, or Instrument of Mortality.</p>
            <p>The King of <hi>SIAM</hi> that died lately was about 59 years of Age; the Character that is given of him in all the printed Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations of the <hi>French</hi> is very advantageous: They say he was, without Contradiction, the greatest Prince that ever Reign'd in <hi>SIAM.</hi> He was of stature somewhat under the middle size, but strait and well shap'd. He had an engaging Air, a sweet and obliging Carriage, especially to Strangers. He was active and brisk, an Enemy of Idleness and Laziness, which seems to be so natural to the <hi>Eastern</hi> Princes, and is accounted by them as the Noblest Prerogative of their Crown. This Prince, on the
<pb n="iii" facs="tcp:57118:3"/> contrary, was always either in the Woods a hunting of Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phants, or in his Palace minding the Affairs of his Kingdom. He was no Lover of War, because it ruin'd his People, whom he tenderly lov'd; but when his Subjects rebell'd, or his neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bouring Princes offer'd him the least Affront, or violated that Respect that was due to him, there was no King in all the <hi>East</hi> that took a more conspicuous Revenge, nor appeared more pas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sionate for Glory. He was desirous of knowing every thing, and having a pregnant and piercing Wit, he easily became Master of what he had a mind to learn. He was magnificent, gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous, and as true a Friend as could be desired. These were the Illustrious Qualities which acquired him the Respect of his Neighbours, the Fear of his Enemies, the Esteem and Love of his Subjects, that was nothing short of Adoration. He was never addicted to those Vices which so commonly reign amongst the Princes of the <hi>East;</hi> nay, he did often severely punish the most considerable <hi>Mandarins,</hi> and principal Officers of the Crown, for being too much given to their Pleasures: So that the most unconquerable Obstacle to the Conversion of those <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dian</hi> and Idolatrous Princes, was not to be found in him, name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, the immoderate Love of Women.</p>
            <p>By the sharpness of his Wit he had discovered the Erro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neousness of the Religion of his Ancestors. And he did not believe an Annihilated God, according to the popular Opinion; or as some of their Doctors say, A God, who weary of govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Heavens, plunges himself in Repose, and for ever buries himself in the forgetfulness of what passes in the world; Nor a Thousand other Superstitions preached by the <hi>Talopins,</hi> who are the Preachers and Priests of the Kingdom. On the contrary, He believ'd that God is Eternal; that his Providence continually governs the World, and disposes of all things. To the same Immortal God he often made his Prayers, and implo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red his Divine Assistance with most profound Reverence at least
<pb n="iv" facs="tcp:57118:4"/> twice a day, for two hours time, in the Morning after he was up, and at Night before he went to rest. Of the truth of this, there is a most Illustrious Monument in that Never-enough to be admired Speech of his to Monsieur <hi>Constance,</hi> in Answer to the <hi>French</hi> Ambassador's Memorial, when he press'd him much to declare himself a Christian; which, because of its singular worth, I think it not amiss to insert it here, as Father <hi>Tachard</hi> has deliver'd it to us in the <hi>5th Book</hi> of his first Voyage to <hi>SIAM,</hi> pag. 309. of the <hi>Paris</hi> Edition, in <hi>Quarto,</hi> which runs thus in <hi>English:</hi>
            </p>
            <p>IN Answer to the <hi>French</hi> Ambassador, you shall tell him from me, That I think my Self extremely obliged to the King of <hi>France</hi> his Master, finding in his Memorial the marks of his most Christian Majesties Royal Friendship; And since the Honour that great Prince hath done me, is already made Publick all over the <hi>East,</hi> I cannot sufficient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly acknowledge his Civility: But that I am extremely troubled that the King of <hi>France,</hi> my good Friend, should propose so difficult a thing unto me, wherewith I am not in the least acquainted; that I refer my Self to the Wisdom of the most Christian King, that he himself may judge of the Importance and Difficulty that occur in so nice a mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, as the Change of a Religion receiv'd and follow'd throughout my whole Kingdom, without Interruption, du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the space of Two thousand two hundred and twenty nine years.</p>
            <p>Besides, it is a matter of Astonishment to me, that the King of <hi>France,</hi> my good Friend, should so much concern himself in an Affair that relates to God, wherein it would seem God do's not at all interest himself, but leaves it whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to our discretion; For could not the true God, that crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the Heavens and the Earth, and all things that are
<pb n="v" facs="tcp:57118:4"/> therein, and hath given them so different Natures and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clinations, when he gave to Men like Bodies and Souls, if he had pleased, have also inspired into them the same Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timents for that Religion they ought to follow, and for that Worship which was most acceptable to him, and make all Nations live and die in the same Laws?</p>
            <p>That Order amongst Men, and that Unity in Religion de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pending absolutely on Divine Providence, who could as easily introduce it into the World, as the diversity of Sects that in all times have been establisht in it; Ought not one to think, that the true God takes as great pleasure to be ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured by different Worships and Ceremonies, as to be glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rify'd by a prodigious number of Creatures, that praise him every one in their own way? Would that Beauty and Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riety which we admire in the Order of Nature, be less admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable in the supernatural Order, or less beseeming the Wis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of God?</p>
            <p>However it be, <hi>continued he,</hi> since we know that God is the absolute Master of the World, and that we are persua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded that nothing comes to pass contrary to his Will, I whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly resign my Person and Dominions into the Arms of the Divine Mercy and Providence, and with all my Heart be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seech his Eternal Wisdom to dispose thereof according to his good Will and Pleasure.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>But after all this Character and Account of his Person and Humour, I cannot learn what his Name was, unless by the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scription of the Letters he sent to the Pope, and to the</hi> French <hi>King in the Year 1688, mentioned in the second Voyage of Father</hi> Tachard: <hi>In his Letter to the</hi> French <hi>King he writes himself thus:</hi>
               <q>SOM DET PRATCHAO CRUNG THEP PRAMHA ANA CON PUJAI.</q>
            </p>
            <pb n="vi" facs="tcp:57118:5"/>
            <p>
               <hi>To the Pope thus:</hi>
               <q>SOM DET PRATCHAO SIA JOV THIA PUJAI.</q>
            </p>
            <p>He never signs his Name in any Letters he writes; the Metal on which his Letters are writ, and which none else in his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom is allow'd to use but himself, is accounted an authentick and unquestionable Proof that the Letters are the Kings. He writes on a Plate of Gold only when he sends Letters to great Kings; and when he writes to inferior and private Persons, it is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly on Paper, to which his Seal is annex'd, which is of dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent bigness, according to the quality of the Person to whom be writes.</p>
            <p>And as for Monsieur <hi>Constance,</hi> besides what is said of him in the following Discourse, I will add some few things taken of other Authors, that are entertaining enough, and deserve to be inserted here.</p>
            <p>Whil'st he was in <hi>England,</hi> and a good while after he had been setled in <hi>SIAM,</hi> he was a good Protestant, but when he fell into the <hi>Jesuits</hi> hands, they soon perverted him, and made him embrace the <hi>Roman Catholick Religion,</hi> and espouse the <hi>French Interest,</hi> to that degree of Zeal that proved so Fatal to him at last. He lived some Years in the Family and Service of one Mr. <hi>White,</hi> a considerable <hi>East-India</hi> Merchant at <hi>SIAM,</hi> who is now in <hi>London,</hi> and continued his Factor when he left <hi>SIAM;</hi> by which means he gather'd some mony, and then set up for himself: The first step he made, was to buy a Ship, and to put to Sea, but had the misfortune to be beat back by bad Weather, and was twice cast away in the Mouth of the River of <hi>SIAM.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Putting to Sea once more, he was shipwrackt the third time, and much more unfortunately, upon the Coast of <hi>Malabar;</hi>
               <pb n="vii" facs="tcp:57118:5"/> there he was in danger of perishing, and could not save, of all he had, above Two thousand Crowns. In this sad Condition, being opprest with grief, weariness and sleep, a remarkable thing hapned to him: He had laid himself down upon the shore, when, whether he was asleep, or awake, he could not tell himself, he fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cied he saw a person full of Majesty, who looking upon him with a smiling Countenance, most obligingly said to him, <hi>Return, Return, from whence you came.</hi> Which words so wrought upon him, as he did often protest to several of his Acquaintance since, That it was impossible for him to sleep all the rest of the Night, his Thoughts being wholly taken up about finding away how to return to <hi>SIAM.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Next Day, whil'st he walked by the Sea-side, reflecting on what he had seen in the Night-time, and uncertain what to think of it, he saw a Man coming towards him dropping wet, with a sad and dejected Countenance: It was an Ambassador of the King of <hi>SIAM,</hi> who, upon his Return from <hi>Persia,</hi> had been Cast away, without saving any thing but his Life; both of them speaking the <hi>Siamese</hi> Tongue, they became soon acquainted with one anothers Adventures. The Ambassador discover'd himself, and told what extreme Necessity he was reduced to. Monsieur <hi>Constance</hi> condoling his Misfortune, offered to carry him back to <hi>SIAM,</hi> and with the 2000 Crowns that he had saved, he bought a small Barque, Cloaths and Provision for their passage. This so obliging a Behaviour charmed the Ambassador of <hi>SIAM,</hi> who, from that time forward, endeavour'd all he could how he might testifie his Gratitude to him. When they arrived at <hi>SIAM,</hi> and the Ambassador had given an Account of his Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotiation and Shipwrack to the chief Minister, he told him all the good Offices which he had receiv'd from Monsieur <hi>Constance,</hi> with so great Applause to his Merit, that the Minister had a mind to know him. He entertain'd him in Discourse, and liked him so well, that he resolved to keep him about him, in which Post
<pb n="viii" facs="tcp:57118:6"/> he soon gain'd the Esteem and Confidence of his Master. This chief Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nister was a Man of Wit, and well versid in Business; but he avoided Trouble as much as he could, and loved his pleasure. It was matter of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding Joy to him, to have found an able, faithful, and industrious Person, on whom he might repose the Cares of his place. The Barcalon dying not long after, he King, would needs put Monsieur <hi>Constance</hi> in his place, but he declin'd it, and told his Majesty, <hi>That that Post would create to him the Envy of all the great Men, and therefore besought him not to raise him higher than he was, for that was the utmost Boundary of his Ambition, accounting himself happy enough, in that he stood fair in his Favours.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>His Modesty, his Skill and Diligence in dispatching Affairs; his Fidelity in managing the publick Revenue, and his Disinterestedness in refusing both the Appointments of his Office, and all Presents from private People, did more and more increase the King's Confidence in him.</p>
            <p>He was very Civil to the <hi>English</hi> on all Occasions, and did them all the friendly Offices that lay in his power. He was very desirous of setling a Trade betwixt that Nation and them, but it was obstructed.</p>
            <p>About two Years ago he sent a very considerable Present to King <hi>James II.</hi> of all the Rarities and valuable Things that the <hi>East-Indies</hi> do produce, estimated to be worth about Six thousand pounds.</p>
            <p>Now that I am talking of Presents, nothing could be more Magnificent, than those that the King of <hi>SIAM</hi> sent to the <hi>French</hi> King in the Year 1685, valued at above Sixty thousand pounds: And, in Requital, the <hi>French</hi> King sent to the King of <hi>SIAM</hi> of the Manufacture of <hi>France,</hi> in Rich Brocards, Looking-Glasses, Watches, Cloaks, and other valuable Things, to the value of above 300000 Crowns; yet nothing was lookt on as a greater Compliment to the King of <hi>SIAM,</hi> than a very fine Caparason of Velvet all richly Embroydered with Silver, Gold, and Pearls, all the Buckles and Rings whereof were of Massy Gold that was sent for the White Elephant, the <hi>Palladiam,</hi> or Tutelar Deity of that Country.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:57118:6"/>
            <head>A RELATION OF THE <hi>Late Great Revolution</hi> IN SIAM, And of the Driving out of the FRENCH.</head>
            <p>BY the various Relations, Embassies and Voyages of <hi>Siam</hi> that have been publisht within these last Four Years, the World has been sufficiently informed of the Intrigues of the <hi>Jesuits</hi> in that Kingdom, which was begun and managed by the means of a certain <hi>Greek</hi> Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian call'd <hi>Constantin Faulcon,</hi> whom the <hi>French</hi> have qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lified with the Title and Dignity <hi>of his Excellency my Lord</hi>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:57118:7"/>
               <hi>Constance.</hi> He was born in <hi>Cephalonia,</hi> a <hi>Greek</hi> Island be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing to the <hi>Venetians,</hi> of a Noble <hi>Venetian,</hi> and of a young Lady of the ancientest Family of the Country; and about the Year 1660, being but Ten Years of Age, he had Sense and Understanding enough to discern the ill Condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion that his Parents Negligence and ill Management had brought their Domestick Affairs into, which put him upon the Resolution of seeking his Fortune abroad, since he could not maintain it according to his Quality at home. The first Adventure he made was into <hi>England,</hi> where he lived some Years, and then went into the <hi>East-Indies,</hi> and was employ'd by some <hi>English</hi> Merchants as their Factor at <hi>Siam.</hi> He continued some time in that Service, and had the good For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune to be known to the chief Minister of State, who in that Country is call'd <hi>Barcalon,</hi> who finding him to be diligent, laborious, and capable of doing Business, brought him into the management of publick Affairs under him; by which means he came to be not only acceptable, but very necessary to the King in the dispatch of several impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant Matters. The Advantage of his <hi>European</hi> Education, and the great Knowledge he had acquired in Trade and Commerce both there and in the <hi>Indies,</hi> making him very considerable, help'd to insinuate him so far into the Favour and good Opinion of the King of <hi>Siam,</hi> that at last, after the death of the <hi>Barcalon,</hi> he was advanced to be one of his chief Ministers, especially for the management of Foreign Affairs.</p>
            <p>The Intrigue was carry'd on at Court, under the plausible Pretext of freeing the Golph of <hi>Siam</hi> from the <hi>Dutch</hi> Yoke, who having <hi>Malacca,</hi> a strong Fort at the En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try of it, in their hands, had imposed a Toll and Duty on all the <hi>Indian</hi> Ships that traded or came into that Bay; but the true Design that (as was believed) lay at the bottom,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:57118:7"/> was first to bring the Kingdom under the <hi>French</hi> Domina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and then to change the establisht Religion of the Country; towards the attainment of which Ends, the said <hi>Greek</hi> had so far prevailed on the King, who having no Sons of his own to succeed him, but two Brothers, as to get him to adopt a young Nobleman that had been bred up in that Christian Religion that the <hi>Jesuits</hi> teach and propagate in the <hi>Indies,</hi> to be his Heir and Successor. It was under this Successor that the Conspiracy was to take Effect.</p>
            <p>The <hi>French</hi> were already become Masters, and in possession of the two chief places that open a passage into that King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom; the one is call'd <hi>Bancock,</hi> which is a great and strong Fortress on the Mouth of the River of <hi>Siam; Margen</hi> is the other place situated on the Frontiers: And as if this had not been enough to please and oblige them, the King allow'd them to have a Command in the Guards about his own Person.</p>
            <p>It was with much Impatience and Resentment that the Officers of State, and the great Men of the Kingdom suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered those pernicious Intrigues to be carry'd on. They could not but well observe, that those great <hi>French</hi> Squa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drons, so fill'd with Numbers of Men, and so plentifully provided with Ammunition, and all Warlike Preparations, aimed at something else, besides the securing of the Trade and Commerce of the <hi>French</hi> Company of Merchants, all whose Stock was not of that Importance, as to occasion the Charges and necessary Expence of one of those Squa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drons; neither were they so filly, or unacquainted with the Affairs abroad, as to believe that those mighty and rich Present that came so frequently from <hi>France,</hi> were sent for no other End, than to make and preserve a strict Friendship and Amity betwixt the Kings of both Nations. They could
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:57118:8"/> not, without some Indignation, bear the specious Discour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses of the <hi>Jesuits,</hi> who would persuade those Oriental Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, that all the Pains they took, the Fatigues and Dangers they had endur'd in coming so far to live amongst them, proceed from no other Principle, but the strong desire they had of doing them good, which was pretended to be the Motive that induced them to come and exercise amongst them those Arts and Sciences that are best understood and practised in <hi>Europe,</hi> such as Physick, Surgery, Astronomy, and the Mathematicks, by the means whereof they hoped to render them capable of being taught the way to Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven.</p>
            <p>On the contrary, they saw that those Missioners had fallen upon the same treacherous and intriguing Methods to over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn their Government, that they had formerly practised in <hi>Japan,</hi> where they made it more their Business to subject that Kingdom to the <hi>Spanish</hi> Domination, (which was then the most potent, and furthest extended in the World) than to bring it under the Obedience of Jesus Christ his Laws. Notwithstanding that the Doctrin of the Gospel had made so great a progress in that vast Empire, that some Princes of the Blood, several of the chief Nobility, and some hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreds of thousands of the People had declared for the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian Religion, and enroll'd themselves amongst the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fessors of it.</p>
            <p>These were the Reflections that the Grandees of <hi>Siam</hi> entertain'd themselves with on this Occasion, but they were willing to stay till the death of the King, before they at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempted the shaking off this Foreign Yoke.</p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:57118:8"/>
            <p>In the Month of <hi>May</hi> 1688, the King happened to fall Sick at his Royal Palace at <hi>Louvo,</hi> the report whereof was no sooner spread abroad, than the Conspiracy broke out, which was contrived by one of the Chief Ministers of State, <hi>Pitrachard</hi> by Name; who, besides his Quality of Great <hi>Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>darin,</hi> was Governor of the Palaces of <hi>Siam</hi> and <hi>Louvo,</hi> and dignified with the Honourable Title of <hi>Opra,</hi> which is one of the most Illustrious and distinguishing Marks of Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour that one is capable of in <hi>Siam.</hi> The discovery of this Plot, the progress it made, and the consequences of it, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the substance of several Letters writ from <hi>Siam</hi> in <hi>Octo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber</hi> 1688, are as follow:</p>
            <p>On the 26th of <hi>May</hi> at Night, <hi>Opra Pitrachard</hi> caused a great many Troops to enter the Castle of <hi>Louvo,</hi> whereby he made himself presently Master of the Person of the King, seized his Adopted Son, and on his two Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, giving it out, and making every one of them in parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular believe, it was to secure the King's Life from a desperate Conspiracy that lately had been discovered against him; but to the three young Princes he further said to every one of them apart, That the King was so ill that he was past all hopes of Recovery, and that he would make it his business to set the Crown on their Heads. This was done on pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose that they might let him go on, and not interrupt him in the execution of so plausible a Design; and it had all the success that he could have wished or hoped.</p>
            <p>Monsieur <hi>Constance</hi> was no sooner acquainted with what had past, and was a carrying on in the Castle, but he went immediately thither, accompanied with a numerous Train of his Friends, and particularly of the <hi>French,</hi> amongst whom
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:57118:9"/> were these Officers of note, Messieurs <hi>de Beauchamp, de Fretteville;</hi> the Chevalier <hi>des Fourbin,</hi> Monsieur <hi>Vandrille,</hi> and <hi>de Luisse,</hi> as he was entring the Castle he told those that were posted round about it, that he was going to see the King; but he did scarcely come within the Gates when they seized on him, and on the <hi>French</hi> Officers, who were all secured and kept together in one of the Apartments of the Palace.</p>
            <p>The next day <hi>Opra Pitrachard</hi> sent for Monsieur <hi>Constance</hi> to come to him, and ordered him to go and tell the <hi>French</hi> Officers that there was no design of keeping them Prisoners, that what was done was occasioned by a most dangerous Plot that they had lately discovered against the Life of the King, but that all the Parties concern'd in it not being as yet fully known, they were under the necessity of securing all Persons of Note, until a clearer discovery should be made; <hi>And as for you Monsieur</hi> Constance (said he, with a certain Air of Authority) <hi>I charge you that you say this, and no more to those</hi> French <hi>Officers; and know, that you shall be narrowly watched and overheard.</hi> This Complemental Visit was only an Artifice that <hi>Opra Pitrachard</hi> used to moderate the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sentments of the <hi>French,</hi> and to hinder them from taking of measures for their common Defence and Security. Monsieur <hi>Constance</hi> went and delievered the Message precisely in the terms he was ordered.</p>
            <p>The King of <hi>Siam</hi> had several Troops of Guards about his Person, whereof one was made up of <hi>Europeans</hi> of different Nations, but especially of the <hi>French.</hi> The <hi>Siams</hi>'s Troop of Guards, consisting of 150 Men, was Commanded by <hi>French</hi> Officers; these were sent to <hi>Thalapson,</hi> a House of Pleasure the King had at some distance from <hi>Louvo,</hi> whither <hi>Opra Pitra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chard</hi>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:57118:9"/> had sent a great Body of the Forces to Encamp, and be in a readiness as occasion should present. Two days after the <hi>French</hi> Officers that had been taken into Custody, and secured at <hi>Louvo,</hi> together with Monsieur <hi>Constance,</hi> were sent thither also under a Strong Guard.</p>
            <p>When matters had thus far proceeded, <hi>Opra Pitrachard</hi> sent again for Monsieur <hi>Constance</hi> to have him brought be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him, and severely reproached him, charging him with Treachery and Perfidiousness against the King and Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of <hi>Siam,</hi> and then caused him to be put to the ordinary and extraordinary Torture, to force him to discover and declare who were his Accomplices in the Management of the Intreague for making the King a Christian, and subje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting the Kingdom to the <hi>French</hi> Power: And when he had continued him several hours in the Torture, he order<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the King's Adopted Son to be brought to the place, and caused his Head to be cut off immediately, and a string to be run through it, and then to be hung about Monsieur <hi>Constance</hi> his Neck, in the manner of <hi>European</hi> Cravats.</p>
            <p>This Tragedy was Acted on the 28th of <hi>May,</hi> the follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing 29 and 30, Monsieur <hi>Constance</hi> was again appli'd to the Torture, in the cruellest manner that could be devised, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the young Prince's Head always hanging on his Breast Night and Day. Thus they continued to Torment him till the 4th of <hi>June,</hi> that he expired under the violence of the Torture.</p>
            <p>His Goods, Family, and all his Effects were also seiz'd every where, and his Family carried into Prison. His La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, after having undergone a severe Examination, and se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Interrogatories put to her, without declaring or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fessing
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:57118:10"/> what they expected or desired, was at last appli'd to the Torture, which she endured several days together; af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter which they threw her into Prison, where she was kept three Months with Iron Chains on her Hands, and Fetters on her Feet; at the end whereof they made her and all her Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily Slaves, in which disgraceful Quality they took off her Irons, open'd the Prison Doors, and turn'd her out.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Opra Pitrachard</hi> who had determin'd with himself to set the Crown on his own Head, after he had once dispatched the King's Adopted Son, and Monsieur <hi>Constance</hi> out of the way, began now to consider how to get rid of the two Princes the King's Brothers, that seem'd to obstruct the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecution of his Design; and this was the Expedient he made use of to bring it about. He made each of them in particular, and severally believe, that what he had acted in all this Revolution, was in order to the bringing and set<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling them on the Throne; but in regard Affairs were not yet in a peaceable and regular Posture, there was a necessi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty for their retiring for some time to <hi>Thalapsan,</hi> until he should use his utmost endeavour to appease them: These poor unfortunate Princes suffered themselves easily to be persuaded by the Magick of those cunning Insinuations and plausible Pretences to go thither; but they never rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched it, being Murthered in the way by a party that was appointed to do that Execution. Then they fell upon all the most considerable Persons that were their Friends and intimate Acquaintance, and caused them to be put to Death in like manner, or imprison'd.</p>
            <p>The next step that <hi>Opra Pitrachard</hi> made, was to set him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self against the Christians, whom he was resolved to drive out of the Kingdom; and to facilitate it the more, he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:57118:10"/> that all the <hi>Portuguese</hi> Christians should meet toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and retire into a little Island near <hi>Siam,</hi> threatning to put all those to Death that should attempt to make their escape out of it.</p>
            <p>The <hi>English</hi> had the Misfortune also to feel the Effects of his Indignation and Rage, for they were first Plundered of all they had, and then thrown into Prison. As for the <hi>French</hi> that were at <hi>Siam</hi> and <hi>Louvo,</hi> he made no open Assault upon them at first, because their numbers were too considerable to be treated as the rest were; and besides he was willing rather to sursprize those that were at <hi>Bancock</hi> and at <hi>Morgen,</hi> then openly to attack them. The most considerable Persons of the <hi>French</hi> Nation that were at <hi>Tha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lapson,</hi> were the Chevaliers <hi>de Cargis,</hi> and <hi>de Fretteville,</hi> Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sieur <hi>de Vandrille,</hi> Mounsieur <hi>de Laisse,</hi> Mounsieur <hi>Bresley,</hi> the Ingineer, and another Inginner; and it was not possible for them to make their escape from <hi>Louvo</hi> as yet: but in conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion, fearing lest in the progress of these Tragical Revolutions, they should meet with the same fate, that the other Christi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans dispersed up and down the Kingdom, had found; they made an escape, and fled towards <hi>Siam,</hi> to the Quarters of the <hi>French</hi> Company, and when they should have the good luck to get thither, their purpose was to have seized on some Ship or other to carry them to the <hi>French</hi> Garison at <hi>Bancock,</hi> where Monsieur <hi>des Farges,</hi> General of the <hi>French</hi> Forces Commanded, and to inform him what had past: But <hi>Opra Pitrachard</hi> being advertised of their flight, early enough to prevent what might follow upon it, sent immediately a detach'd Body of 6 or 7000 Men, Arm'd as if they were ready to give Battel. These few Officers, tho' the bravest and most determin'd Men of their Nation, were much sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priz'd to see so early in the Morning, and within two
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:57118:11"/> Leagues of <hi>Siam;</hi> so great a Detachment of the Army before and behind them, to hinder their getting into the Town; and making a vertue of necessity, they put them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves into a poisture of Defence, resolving to sell their Lives at as dear a rate as they could; but some <hi>Mandarins</hi> coming up to them, told them they were in no danger, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard they assur'd them, they were come, not only to do them no harm themselves, but to prevent their receiving any from others and their business was to bring them back to <hi>Louvo,</hi> as the King had expresly commanded them: The <hi>French</hi> Gentlemen were soon overcome by the power of so fine and obliging Expressions, and presently surrendred themselves into their hands; for to do otherwise was not possible for them, there being no proportion betwixt the fewness of their number, and so great a Body as they had to dispute with. And the truth on't is, they were treated the first day with kindness and civility enough; but it was not so the next, for they strip'd them of all, and ti'd them to Horse-Tails, in which miserable condition they forc'd them to march, and in great Ceremony brought them back to <hi>Lou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vo,</hi> treating them most outragiously all along as they went, in so much that Monsieur <hi>Bresley</hi> the Ingineer dy'd soon after, and the rest had much ado to outlive the Miseries and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dignities they suffered. They no sooner arriv'd at <hi>Louvo,</hi> but they were Chain'd two and two together, by the Neck, and so thrown into Prison; all their Domesticks were treated in like manner, as well as all the other <hi>French</hi> that staid at <hi>Louvo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>All this was contrived and executed with that diligence and secrecy, that may seem very surprizing and unaccoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table to those that hear it: For the <hi>French</hi> that were at <hi>Ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cock</hi> and <hi>Morgen,</hi> had not the least knowledge of what had
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:57118:11"/> been done in the two Cities of <hi>Siam</hi> and <hi>Louvo,</hi> which was like to have lost them all.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Opra Pitrachard</hi> having now taken his measures, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termined to destroy the <hi>French</hi> one way or other, and since he would not venture upon the doing of it by open force, was resolved to try what Cunning and Surprize could do. Wherefore he sent one <hi>Manpai,</hi> who had been the year be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in <hi>France,</hi> in Quality of first Ambassador, and since his return was honour'd with the title of <hi>Barcalon,</hi> or Chief Minister of State, to <hi>Bancock,</hi> to perswade Monsieur <hi>des Farges</hi> General of the <hi>French</hi> to come to him, and to tell him that it was the King's express pleasure that he should immediately come and confer with him about some Affairs of the last importance, and make what haste he possibly could to be at <hi>Louvo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The General, that was altogether ignorant of what had been done in all this great and sudden Revolution, and sus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecting no fraud, believed very readily what the <hi>Barca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon</hi> had told him, and that the King had sent for him, as on other occasions he had often done before; set out from <hi>Bancock</hi> the 7th of <hi>June,</hi> and went by Water; but he had hardly gone two Leagues from the place, when he perceived that some extraordinary business was in agitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and apprehended there might be some design of putting some indignity upon him: For he could not imagine why he was surrounded with such a great number of Barges and Galleys, Arm'd with Stones and Field-Pieces, that perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tually accompani'd him till he came to <hi>Siam;</hi> where he no sooner arriv'd, but he was immediately taken out, and put into a Palanquin or close Litter, and carried to <hi>Louvo,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Guarded by several Troops of Armed Men; all this
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:57118:12"/> still encreased his astonishment, and the more, because he was not wont to be hurri'd nor conducted in so Military a manner, when the King wanted him, or ordered him to come to him, but he had always the priviledge of going with great freedom, and less attended.</p>
            <p>When he came to <hi>Louvo,</hi> he was straight led to the King's Palace, without allowing him the liberty of going first to the <hi>Jesuits</hi> House to Repose and Refresh himself, as he desired, tho' his intention was rather to be somewhat in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form'd, and know the posture of present Affairs, which he thought were much altered. The same day of his arri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>val he received several Visits from the <hi>Mandarins,</hi> and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Supper he had one from <hi>Opra Pitrachard,</hi> with whom he discoursed some time, and, amongst other things, the <hi>Opra</hi> told him, with an unusual Air of Pride and Haughti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>That the King had caused Monsieur</hi> Constance <hi>to be put to Death for many hainous Crimes and Faults he had been found guilty of, in the management of those Employments he was entrusted with; and that the King would give him his Place, knowing him to be a Man of great Integrity, Faithfulness, and good Ʋnderstanding in the management of Affairs, and in whom he reposed great Confidence and Trust.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>He further told him, <hi>That the King was engaged in a War against the</hi> Cochinchinois, <hi>and the People of</hi> Laos; <hi>That there was a necessity of sending for all the</hi> French <hi>Forces to joyn in a Body, and march against the Enemy, to hinder the Invasion that the Kingdom was threatened with; and that he had also writ to Monsieur</hi> Bruham, <hi>Governour of</hi> Morgen, <hi>to the same purpose, to hasten to</hi> Louvo, <hi>with all his Troops:</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:57118:12"/>
            <p>Monsieur <hi>des Farges</hi> saw plainly now that these Propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sals were nothing but a meer Contrivance, and like so ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Snares that they had laid to catch him; which he was fully convinc'd of in a very little time afterwards, as well by the distinct Information he receiv'd from several of his Friends, that by <hi>Opra Pitrachard</hi>'s express Order, had leave to make him a Visit, as by Letters that came to him from his Officers: And began not to consider with himself, what he must do to get out of the Danger that his good Nature and Fidelity to the King had so unluckily brought him into; and the best Expedient he could think of, was to send this Answer to <hi>Opra Pitrachard:</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>That the King of</hi> France, <hi>his Master, had sent him to serve the King of</hi> SIAM, <hi>and that he was now ready to obey his Commands: But that he thought it highly ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessary to go himself in person to</hi> Bancock, <hi>to bring the Sol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers with him, in regard that the Officers that commanded in his Absence, would not quit the Fortress upon a bare Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This seem'd so reasonable, and to carry so much proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility with it, that he presently obtain'd leave to return to the Fort; but on condition to leave his two Sons that came along with him, as Hostages for the performance of his promise. But before he left <hi>Louvo,</hi> he was much press'd by the <hi>Opra</hi> to write to Monsieur <hi>de Bruham,</hi> and fain would he have been excused from complying with him in it: And told him, <hi>That unless he sent an Officer of his own to carry the Letter, it would signifie nothing, nor be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garded.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="14" facs="tcp:57118:13"/>
            <p>But it was to no purpose to insist on such a Condition, for it was positively deny'd him, and yet write he must, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing under an unavoidable necessity of doing it; yet in writing, he did so disguise his Hand and Stile, by chusing such extravagant Terms and unusual Expressions, as that Monsieur <hi>Braham</hi> might know, in case the Letter came to his hands, there was some further Mystery in it, and that he was not to give Credit to it; and, by good Providence, it fell out just as he could have wished, the Letter be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing received and understood in the Sense it was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>signed.</p>
            <p>Monsieur <hi>des Farges</hi> return'd no sooner to <hi>Bancock,</hi> but he abandon'd the Little Fort, and drew off all the <hi>French</hi> into the Great Fort, not having Men enough to hold out in both places. All the Houses that were near to it, he cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed to be pillag'd, and then burnt; and all the Cannon that he could not carry away or use, to be nail'd or broken. And because he had not time enough to demolish or raze the Fort, by reason of the great number of Forces that <hi>Opra Pitrachard</hi> sent after him, and follow'd him to take posses<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion of the place; he did what was possible to ruin it all to pieces with his Cannon.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Opra Pitrachard</hi> perceiving by this, that Monsieur <hi>des Farges</hi> had discover'd his Rebellious Designs and Practices, and that there was no prospect or hopes of his Return with his Soldiers to <hi>SIAM,</hi> he sent down an Army of about Threescore thousand Men, made up of <hi>Mahumetans, Chi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neses,</hi> and <hi>Malayans,</hi> against the Fort of <hi>Bancock,</hi> to besiege the <hi>French</hi> in't, with Orders to cut all their Throats. But such was the Resolution and Bravery wherewithal they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sended themselves, that this open Investing and Attacking
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:57118:13"/> of them, proved as Unsuccessful, as the Artifices that were used to Trepan them to come to <hi>SIAM</hi> were in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>effectual: For when so vast an Army had endeavoured all they could, during two Months close Siege, by frequent Attacks and Storming, to force their Entry into the place, and had been always beat off with great Loss, by the hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful of <hi>French,</hi> who were not in all above Three hundred, he saw himself obliged, at last, to send to the General, and ask Conditions of Peace.</p>
            <p>During this Siege, all the <hi>French</hi> who were at <hi>Siam</hi> and <hi>Louvo</hi> were made close Prisoners, and treated with the greatest extremity of Rigor and Severity, without consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration of Quality or Age. Nor could the Bishop of <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tellopolis,</hi> who had lived long amongst them, and was the Apostolick Vicar in the greatest part of of the <hi>East-Indies,</hi> be exempted from his share of the common Calamity that fell upon his Profession and Countrey-Men: For when <hi>Opra Pitrachard</hi> saw he could not recover <hi>Bancock</hi> out of the hands of the <hi>French</hi> by force, he caus'd the old Bishop to be sent for, and conducted to the Fort-and there to be strip'd and ti'd to a Gibbet, with a Halter about his Neck, and fastned at the place where the <hi>French</hi> Cannon were most levell'd, and did most execution, hoping that the sight of so moving a Spectacle, and the consideration they had of the Person of their Bishop, should prevail with them to mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate the fury of their Guns, intermit their Firing, and hearken to a Treaty of Peace.</p>
            <p>All the <hi>French</hi> Jesuits and Missionary Priests that were any where in the Kingdom, were seiz'd, and carri'd Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soners to <hi>Louvo,</hi> being Accused of Sedition and Treason against the Government; all their Goods, Furniture, and Effects were likewise seiz'd and confiscated.</p>
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:57118:14"/>
            <p>All this could not be acted without coming to the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of Monsieur <hi>de Bruham,</hi> Governor of <hi>Morgen,</hi> having now been fully inform'd from several hands of what had past both at <hi>Louvo</hi> and <hi>Siam,</hi> he began to consider how to extricate himself out of the great and iminent danger he was every where surrounded with; for he had but fifty two Souldiers, three Captains, three Lieutenants, and three Ensigns in all, to Guard a large Fortress that was open on all sides. The best thing he could think of in that ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremity, was to seize a small Frigat of 26 Guns, belong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the King of <hi>Siam,</hi> to save himself and his Men upon, when he should be driven to his last shifts: This he hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pily executed towards the end of <hi>June,</hi> and it was of great use to him in the conclusion of the Affair: For when he had been Besieged and closely Attack'd for seventeen days together, by an Army of Twelve thousand Men, assaulting them often, and as often repulsed; and wanting Water and other necessary Provisions, without any possible hopes of being relieved or refreshed, he was constrain'd, at last, to abandon the place, and carry all his Men, and what conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niently else he could, on Board the Frigat, and so got safe off.</p>
            <p>On the 25th of <hi>July,</hi> the Bishop of <hi>Metellopolis</hi> being released out of the miserable and dangerous Circumstan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces he was put into, before <hi>Bancock</hi> was sent into the place, to obtain a Commission and full Power from the General Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sieur <hi>des Forges,</hi> to negotiate a Treaty of Peace with such persons as <hi>Opra Pitrachard</hi> should appoint for that purpose; which was soon granted him, and next day he return'd to <hi>SIAM</hi> to conclude it.</p>
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:57118:14"/>
            <p>A Little time after, News was brought that the King of <hi>Siam</hi> was dead, without telling either the day or man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of his Death: Whereupon <hi>Opra Pitrachard</hi> began to prepare for his Coronation, and about five days after he set out from <hi>Louvo</hi> in great State and Magnificence, and came to <hi>Siam,</hi> where he had himself Crown'd King with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any Dispute or Opposition, about the beginning of <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gust</hi> 1688.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>September 30.</hi> News was brought that a Peace was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded and sign'd betwixt the new King and the <hi>French,</hi> on the following Conditions.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>That the</hi> French <hi>should surrender the Fort of</hi> Bancock.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>That all the</hi> French <hi>should have leave to depart the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>That they should have two Frigats belonging to the</hi> French <hi>Company; a Ship of the</hi> French <hi>King's called the</hi> Auriflame, <hi>and a fourth of 74 Guns that the King of</hi> Siam <hi>was to give to Monsieur</hi> des Farges <hi>to Embarque on, and Transport them out of the King of</hi> Siam'<hi>s Dominions.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This is the substance of what is contain'd in the several Letters dated from <hi>Siam, October</hi> last was twelve-moneth; and by the Relation we have, by Advice from the Coast of <hi>Coramandel</hi> of the 20th of <hi>February</hi> last, we are further inform'd, That Monsieur <hi>des Farges</hi> was arrived on that Coast with the four Ships, having all the <hi>French</hi> as well Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular and Military, as the Ecclesiasticks on board them, that were any where to be heard of or known to be in the
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:57118:15"/> Kingdom of <hi>Siam,</hi> and that the King had publisht a De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration, severely prohibiting any <hi>French</hi> to stay in the Kingdom; and threatning that if any one of them should be found to stay behind, they should be immediately upon discovery put to Death; and all the <hi>Europeans</hi> that should harbour or conceal them, should be treated with the same rigor.</p>
            <p>Other Letters do further add, That Monsieur <hi>des Farges</hi> had before his departure from <hi>Bancock,</hi> deliver'd up into the hands of the present King of <hi>Siam,</hi> the Unfortunate Widow of Monsieur <hi>Constance,</hi> upon a fancy that the Jesu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>its had put into his head; That she being a Christian, and extreamly beloved by the King's Son, will marry him, and contribute her endeavours to make him a Christian; with which plaufible Imaginations those good Fathers flatter themselves, and hope once more to be re-established in that Kingdom with no less Advantages of Power, Credit and Fortune than they had before.</p>
            <p>And, that when the Treaty was sign'd betwixt the King of <hi>Siam</hi> and the <hi>French</hi> General, all the <hi>French</hi> and <hi>English</hi> that were made Prisoners at <hi>Louvo,</hi> were the next day af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Conducted to <hi>Siam,</hi> and set at Liberty.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="diary">
            <pb n="19" facs="tcp:57118:15"/>
            <head>
               <hi>A</hi> DIARY <hi>of one of the</hi> French Officers <hi>that served at</hi> Morgen <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Command of Monsieur</hi> de Bru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham, <hi>containing several particulars relating to the former Discourse.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>ON the 25th of <hi>June</hi> 1688, being upon Duty, and Commanding a Company of fifty <hi>Siamese</hi> Soldiers in the little Fort of <hi>Morgen,</hi> I was seized on by my own Men, and made Prisoner, and for four days together was fastened to a Stake, with Iron Chains about my Body, on my Hands and Feet.</p>
            <p>On the 29th I was carried out to see if I could know and discover some <hi>French</hi> Men that had been killed during the vigorous Defence that Monsieur <hi>de Bruham</hi> made in the Fort, and whilst he was drawing off his Men out of it, and retiring into the Frigat, upon which he made his escape; for there were about thirteen dead Bodies lying upon the place. And when I had told them all that I thought proper for them to know upon that matter, the <hi>Mandarins</hi> that Commanded in the Army that besieged the Fort, gave or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders to put me to the Torture, to force me to declare and make information, that I had often heard Monsieur <hi>de Bru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> say, <hi>That his being and commanding at</hi> Morgen <hi>was al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together unknown to the King of</hi> Siam, <hi>and by the order of Monsieur</hi> Constance <hi>only, on purpose to make himself Master of the Countrey; and that Monsieur</hi> de Bruham <hi>expected seve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Ships with Men, Arms, and Ammunition from</hi> France,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:57118:16"/>
               <hi>to enable him to carry on that Design more effectually.</hi> I was appli'd to, and kept in the torture four hours toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
            <p>On the 7th of <hi>July,</hi> the <hi>Mandarins</hi> made me go for <hi>Siam</hi> in the company of a <hi>French</hi> Soldier call'd <hi>Picquard,</hi> who had the misfortune to be made a Prisoner the same day that Monsieur <hi>de Bruham</hi> made his Retreat from <hi>Morgen;</hi> and tho' we were but two Men, and both in Chains, yet such was the mistrust they entertain'd of us, that they would needs send above Sixty Soldiers to guard us thither.</p>
            <p>On the 17th I came to <hi>Siam,</hi> and on the 19th was brought to <hi>Louvo.</hi> The first place they brought me into, was the great Hall where the <hi>Barcalon</hi> was sitting with many <hi>Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>darins</hi> about him. who commanded me to be Interrogated very strictly upon several Matters relating to Monsieur <hi>Bruham.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Next Morning I was informed by a Missionary Priest, who accidentally discovered the place where I was kept Prisoner, that the Bishop of <hi>Metellopolis</hi> was gone to <hi>Ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cock,</hi> by the express command of <hi>Opra Pitrachard,</hi> to nego<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiate a Treaty of Peace with Monsieur <hi>des Farges</hi> our Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral, and that they were in daily expectation of hearing of the conclusion of it. This was the first time that I had any tolerable ground to entertain my self with the hopes of Life, since my falling into their hands; for 'till now I gave all for lost.</p>
            <p>On the 25th the Bishop return'd to <hi>Louvo</hi> with full power from Monsieur <hi>des Farges,</hi> to Treat about a Peace;
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:57118:16"/> and from that time forward <hi>Opra Pitrachard</hi> began to desist from his cruel Treatment of the <hi>French,</hi> and other Christi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans that were in his power.</p>
            <p>In the Month of <hi>July,</hi> the King of <hi>Siam</hi> hapned to die, but the manner of it, nor the certain day, being as yet un<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>known, <hi>Opra Pitrac<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> set out from <hi>Louvo</hi> on the last day of the Month to <hi>Siam,</hi> where he was Crown'd with great Ceremony, and without any opposition. Next day after the Coronation, he order'd all the <hi>French</hi> and <hi>English</hi> that were at <hi>Siam</hi> and <hi>Louvo</hi> to be set at li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty.</p>
            <p>On the 3d of <hi>August</hi> I arrived at <hi>Siam,</hi> with four other <hi>French</hi> Officers, namely Messieurs <hi>de Fretteville, de Van<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drille, des Carges,</hi> and <hi>de Laisse.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>On the 9th <hi>Opra Pitrachard</hi> now King of <hi>Siam,</hi> sent us all five to <hi>Bancock,</hi> not to our own General, as we hoped, but to his General that Commanded the <hi>Malayans,</hi> who kept us Prisoners almost a Month; and all the <hi>French</hi> that were left at <hi>Siam</hi> were delivered into the Custody of the Jesuits, and of the Chief Factor of the <hi>French</hi> Company of Merchants, to be reponsible for them.</p>
            <p>The King being resolved to have a Peace concluded at any Rate, sent us at last to Monsieur <hi>des Farges,</hi> who would hearken to no Treaty, without allowing us the benefit of being comprehended in it, by which means our liberty was obtain'd.</p>
            <p>On the 30th of <hi>September</hi> the Peace was concluded and sign'd. Two days after Monsieur <hi>des Farges,</hi> our General,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:57118:17"/> sent me from <hi>Bancock</hi> to <hi>Morgen,</hi> to see what was become of Monsieur <hi>de Bruham,</hi> and to acquaint him that the Peace was concluded. The King of <hi>SIAM</hi> gave me a <hi>Mandarin</hi> to accompany me, and to provide for me such things as were necessary during my Journey.</p>
            <p>On the 12th of <hi>October</hi> I arriv'<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>orgen,</hi> where I stay'd not long, because I could learn nothing about Monsieur <hi>de Bruham.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>On the First of <hi>November</hi> I Embarqued on a small Frigat of the King of <hi>SIAM</hi>'s, and went upon the Rivers of <hi>Tanay, Musavan,</hi> and <hi>Sorian,</hi> in the Kingdom of <hi>Pegu,</hi> thinking to have found him in some of those places: But missing of him there, I was obliged to pass by the Islands of <hi>Rey,</hi> and to go on shore at <hi>Seroide,</hi> where, by some cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain marks, I knew that Monsieur <hi>Bruham</hi> had touch'd, and especially by some pieces of the <hi>French</hi> Soldiers Cloaths that seem'd to have been left there on purpose to give us notice of their passage that way.</p>
            <p>On the 12th of <hi>November</hi> I return'd again to <hi>Morgen,</hi> where finding a Ship belonging to the Royal <hi>French</hi> Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany, call'd <hi>The Cocq,</hi> commanded by Monsieur <hi>Darmagnan,</hi> I Embarqued thereupon two days after, to go to <hi>Pondichery,</hi> where I was ordered to wait for Monsieur <hi>des Farges,</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oording to the Instructions he gave me at parting from <hi>Bancock.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:57118:17"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>